so why do we want a multiprocessor why
not just use uniprocessors well first
our uniprocessors
would already be for wide when we got to
about four to six wide is when we switch
to using multi processors and that's
because once you get to this point you
get diminishing returns from making the
uniprocessor even wider you can make it
execute let's say six or eight
instructions per cycle but you don't get
as much from that extension as you did
from for example making it from two to
four wide and that's because we get
diminishing returns if you remember your
endures law there will be things that
benefit from this such as programs that
have a lot of parallelism between
instructions and then there are things
that don't benefit from this such as
programs that have a lot of dependencies
so they have to run things one at a time
things that are four wide already are
already making the parallel parts fast
whereas the one at a time parts are not
accelerated so by the time you get here
you already have a lot of your program
suffer from not enough parallelism to
benefit from either four or even six
wide another problem with unit
processors if we make them even fancier
is to make them faster we have to jack
up the frequency to do that we have to
raise the voltage from what it would be
if we use the lower frequency and when
we do both of these the power
consumption grows up cubically so even
if we increase the frequency by not too
much we would end up burning our
processor so we don't really want to
make our unit processors be clocked
twice as fast as before and we don't
want to make them much wider than they
already are
but Moore's law continues we get twice
the transistors every 18 months for the
same cost as before and in the same area
as before so we want to benefit from
this and improve the overall performance
but we no longer can do it this way so
what do we do we just double the number
of cores every 18 months that allows us
to have the course that are not getting
wider that are not getting up in
frequency too much and yet the overall
computational performance of the chip is
improving with Moore's law
so we can get approximately a doubling
of overall performance every 18 months
that is only if we assume that we can
use all the cores if we only have one
program with one thread then we are
really using only one of the cores it
doesn't matter if the number of cores
doubles because we are still using one
of those cores so we need programs that
are parallel in order to exploit our
many core processors that we are getting
but if we do we continue the trend of
scaling performance up exponentially to
put this in another way we have multi
processors today not because we think
that we would rather have twice the
cores than twice the unit processor
performance it's always preferable to
have a uniprocessor a single core that
is twice as fast as before then having
two cores that are just as fast as
before but we ran out of things that we
can do with uni processors so after a
long string of years where we were doing
this just getting better unit processors
we had to switch to this if we want to
get performance improvement